Thomas G. Paterson Papers
© 2003 University of Connecticut
Thomas G. Paterson Papers.
1836-2002.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Paterson, Thomas G.
40 linear feet.
Thomas Graham Paterson received his Bachelors degree from the University of New Hampshire in 1963, and his Masters and Doctoral degrees from the University of California, Berkeley in 1964 and 1968, respectively. As an historian, educator, and author, he has written and co-written a number of books and articles, and has also acted as an editor for various other publications. Paterson is known primarily for his contributions to the history of the Cold War with a focus on Cuba, as well as United States foreign relations in general.
MSS19980365
Biography
Thomas Graham Paterson was born 4 March 1941 in Oregon City, Oregon. He received his Bachelors degree from the University of New Hampshire in 1963, and his Masters and Doctoral degrees from the University of California at Berkeley in 1964 and 1968, respectively. Paterson is known primarily for his contributions to Cold War history with an emphasis on United States-Cuba relations, as well as the study of United States foreign relations in general.
A prolific author, Paterson has written and co-written numerous books and articles, and has also served as an editor for several books and scholarly journals, including Diplomatic History and the Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations (1997), for which he was a contributing editor. He has published several articles and book reviews in newspapers, magazines, and newsletters, as well as scholarly journals such as the Journal of American History, The New England Journal of History, Diplomatic History, the New England Quarterly, and the American Historical Review. He is a member of a multiple of historical and scholarly associations, including the American Historical Association, the Organization of American Historians, the New England Historical Association, and the Society for Historians of American Foreign Relations (SHAFR), the last of which he was president in 1987.
Paterson is the recipient of a number of fellowships and research grants. He has appeared on television and radio programs, and has delivered an impressive number of lectures throughout the United States, as well as Canada, China, Cuba, Venezuela, New Zealand, Great Britain, Colombia, and Russia. He taught both graduate and undergraduate level History courses at the University of Connecticut from 1967 through 1997. Aside from his teaching duties, Paterson was also a member of several different University and History Department committees. Paterson has been Professor Emeritus since his retirement from teaching at UConn in 1997.
Scope and Content
The collection consists primarily of correspondence, notes, articles and papers, and research materials, such as photocopies of government documents and published works. The collection is centered around the Paterson's own writings, research and professional activities.
Organization
Series I: Books ( 1836-1998 )contains all extant materials pertaining to Paterson's books and is arranged in chronological order according to the year in which the first edition of each book or of the first edition of the first book in a series was published.
Series II: Articles and book chapters ( 1962-1997 ).
Series III: Lectures and panels ( 1964-2002 ) is arranged in chronological order according to the date when the lecture was given, not when it was written. Several of the lectures included were given at various times.
Series IV: University of Connecticut files ( 1967-2002 ).
Series V: Professional activities ( 1967-2002 ).
Series VI: Research materials ( 1839-1997 ) The sub-section of Series VI entitled "Notes, documents, essays: U.S. foreign relations topics" is arranged alphabetically.
Series VII: Photographs, negatives, and microfiche ( 1944-1968 ).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to American politics, particularly in Connecticut, and the University's history. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Arrangement
The collection was arranged, when possible, in accordance with the original order in which it was received from the donor. When necessary, materials were rearranged into the proper chronological or alphabetical order. The materials were arranged chronologically for the most part and, at times, alphabetically within the chronological order. Original folder descriptions were retained. Series VI contains a subseries concerning relations between the United States and Castro's Cuba, this portion of the collection has been microfilmed by Scholarly Resources (1998) and is available on microfilm in the Homer Babbidge Library Reference Microform Collection.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The research portion of the collection was donated by Dr. Paterson to the Dodd Research Center in November 1997. Subsequent donations were made in 1998, 1999 and 2002.
Accruals
The Paterson Papers were received in five accessions, from 1998 through 2002. All but the most recent (two boxes and several folders) are represented in this finding aid.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Books, undated, 1836-1998
  - Sales figures for various books, 1986-1989 (Box 1:1)
  - Origins of the Cold War published 1970
    - First edition: correspondence, undated, 1967-1970 (Box 1:2)
    - Second edition: correspondence, undated, 1961-1974 (Box 1:3)
    - Third edition: correspondence, undated, 1989-1990 (Box 1:4)
    - Fourth edition, undated, 1990-1998 (Box 1:5)
  - Cold War Critics, published 1971
    - Correspondence, undated, 1968-1970 (Box 1:6)
    - Correspondence: critiques, undated, 1969-1970 (Box 1:7)
    - Sales figures, undated, 1971-1979 (Box 1:8)
  - American Imperialism and Anti-Imperialism published 1973
    - Sales figures, 1973-1982 (Box 1:9)
  - Containment and the Cold War published 1973
    - Sales figures, 1973-1984 (Box 1:10)
  - Soviet-American Confrontation published 1973
    - General, undated, 1968-1976 (Box 1:11)
    - Sales figures, 1973-1993 (Box 1:12)
  - American Foreign Policy: A History published 1977
    - Correspondence, undated, 1973-1977 (Box 1:13)
    - First edition: pictures/ illustrations, ca. 1976 (Box 1:14)
    - Second edition, undated, 1977-1982 (Box 1:15)
    - Second edition: promotion and general, 1982-1984 (Box 1:16)
    - Third edition, undated, 1982-1987 (Box 1:17)
    - Third edition: correspondence, undated, 1990 april - September (Box 1:18)
    - Fourth edition (American Foreign Relations), undated, 1988-1994 (Box 1:19)
      - Research notes on multiple topics organized by subject (Tray 7), undated (Box 37-38)
  - Major Problems in American History series
    - Correspondence, undated, 1972-1988 (Box 1:20)
    - Correspondence, 1989-1994 (Box 1:21)
    - Development and marketing, undated, 1984-1990 (Box 1:22)
    - Permissions, undated, 1976 January (Box 2:23)
    - Major Problems in...
      - American Foreign Policy published 1978
        - Second edition, undated, 1977-1983 (Box 2:24)
        - Volume I: to 1914, undated, 1976-1977 (Box 2:25)
        - Third edition, undated, 1987-1988 (Box 2:26)
        - Fourth edition, undated, 1992-1994 (Box 2:27)
        - Research materials, undated, 1836-1982 (Box 2:28)
        - Research materials, undated, 1838-1987 (Box 2:29)
      - American Women's History published 1989
        - General, undated, 1986-1987 (Box 2:30)
      - The History of the American West published 1989
        - General, undated, 1985-1991 (Box 2:31)
      - The History of the American South published 1990
        - First edition, undated, 1985-1989 (Box 2:32)
        - Second edition, 1995-1998 (Box 2:33)
      - The History of American Workers published
        - General, undated, 1988-1990 (Box 2:34)
      - The History of the Vietnam War published 1990
        - General, 1986-1989 (Box 2:35)
      - The Civil War and Reconstruction published 1991
        - First edition, undated, 1988-1989 (Box 2:36)
        - Second edition, 1996-1997 (Box 2:37)
      - American Constitutional History published 1992
        - General, undated, 1988-1990 (Box 2:38)
      - The Early Republic, 1787-1848 published 1992
        - General, 1988-1990 (Box 2:39)
      - The Era of the American Revolution, 1760-1791 published 1992
        - General, undated, 1985-1990 (Box 2:40)
      - American Colonial History published 1993
        - General, undated, 1986-1990 (Box 2:41)
      - American Immigration and Ethnic History published 1998
        - General, undated, 1988-1996 (Box 3:42)
      - American Military History published 1998
        - Correspondence, undated, 1990-1995 (Box 3:43)
        - Outlines and reviews, 1996-1997 (Box 3:44)
        - Outlines and reviews, 1992-1997 (Box 3:45)
      - The History of American Technology published 1998
        - General, undated, 1988-1993 (Box 3:46)
        - General, 1994-1997 (Box 3:47)
      - American History, 1920-1945 published 1999
        - General, undated, 1989-1998 (Box 3:48)
      - Mexican American History published 1999
        - General, undated, 1993-1997 (Box 3:49)
  - On Every Front published 1979
    - Research notes organized by subject (Tray 5), undated (Box 35-36)
    - First edition: correspondence, undated, 1971-19798 (Box 3:50)
    - Revised edition, undated, 1980-1992 (Box 3:51)
  - A People and A Nation published 1982
    - First edition: "getting started": correspondence, undated, 1975-1976 (Box 3:52)
    - First edition: "getting started": correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 3:53)
    - First edition: "getting started": notes, articles, undated, 1976-1978 (Box 3:54)
    - First edition: correspondence related to publication, undated, 1978-1979 (Box 3:55)
    - First edition: correspondence related to publication, 1980-1982 (Box 3:56)
    - First edition: notes, planning, undated, 1978-1980 (Box 3:57)
    - First edition: author information forms, undated, 1981 April - May (Box 3:58)
    - First edition: author interactions comments on others' chapters), undated, 1978-1980 (Box 4:59)
    - First edition: sample pages, undated (Box 4:60)
    - First edition: sales promotion, 1981-1983 (Box 4:61)
    - First edition: comparisons to other texts, undated, 1980 June 13 (Box 4:62)
    - Brief edition (first edition) correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 4:63)
    - Second edition: correspondence, undated, 1982-1984 (Box 4:64)
    - Second edition: correspondence, 1985 January - September (Box 4:65)
    - Second edition: correspondence on revisions, undated, 1983-1985 (Box 4:66)
    - Second edition: reviewers' comments and revision notes, 1983-1985 (Box 4:67)
    - Second edition: author interactions (comments and revisions), chapters 1-12, undated, 1983-1984 (Box 4:68)
    - Second edition: author interactions (comments and revisions), chapters 13-24, undated, 1983-1985 (Box 4:69)
    - Second edition: author interactions (comments and revisions), chapters 25-35, 1983-1985 (Box 4:70)
    - Second edition: sample pages, undated (Box 4:71)
    - Third edition: correspondence, undated, 1984-1987 (Box 4:72)
    - Third edition: correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 4:73)
    - Third edition: comments and reviews, undated, 1988-1989 (Box 4:74)
    - Third edition: comments and reviews, undated, 1985-1989 (Box 4:75)
    - Third edition: maps, charts, figures, undated, 1989 March - July (Box 4:76)
    - Fourth edition: correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 4:77)
    - Fourth edition: notes and revisions, undated, 1991-1992 (Box 4:78)
    - Fourth edition: appendix, undated (Box 4:79)
    - Fourth edition: Houghton Mifflin sales meeting, Aug 16 1993, undated, 1991-1994 (Box 4:80)
    - Fourth edition: Brief edition, 1994 May - November (Box 4:81)
    - Fifth edition: correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 4:82)
    - Fifth edition: revision planning meeting, 1994-1995 (Box 4:83)
    - Fifth edition: revisions, comments, reviews, chapters 1-26, undated, 1994-1996 (Box 4:84)
    - Fifth edition: revisions, reviews, chapters 27-34, undated, 1989-1996 (Box 4:85)
    - Fifth edition: preface, 1995-1997 (Box 4:86)
    - Fifth edition: Houghton Mifflin sales meeting, Jan 6 1998, 1998 January 6 (Box 4:87)
  - Meeting the Communist Threat published 1988
    - Ads and reviews, undated, 1985-1989 (Box 5:88)
  - Kennedy's Quest for Victory: American Foreign Policy 1961-1963 published 1989
    - General, undated, 1985-1988 (Box 5:89)
  - Explaining the History of American Foreign Relations published 1991
    - General, 1989-1991 (Box 5:90)
  - Imperial Surge: The United States Abroad, the 1890's-early 1900's published 1992
    - General, undated, 1990-1991 (Box 5:91)
  - Contesting Castro: The United States and the Triumph of the Cuban Revolution published 1994
    - Bibliography cards organized by subject (Tray 8), undated (Box 39)
    - Research notes organized by subject (Tray 10), 1961 (Box 41)
    - General, undated, 1992-1993 (Box 5:92)
    - Illustrations, undated, 1992-1993 (Box 5:93)
    - Promotion, undated, 1993-1995 (Box 5:94)
    - Corrections, undated, 1995-1996 (Box 5:95)
  - Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations published 1997
    - Correspondence, undated, 1992-1993 (Box 5:96)
    - Correspondence, 1994 January - August (Box 5:97)
    - Correspondence, 1994 September - December (Box 5:98)
    - Correspondence, undated, 1995 January - March (Box 5:99)
    - Correspondence, 1995 March - April (Box 5:100)
    - Correspondence, 1995 May - December (Box 5:101)
    - Correspondence, 1996 January - May (Box 5:102)
    - Correspondence, 1996 May - December (Box 5:103)
    - Administrative, undated, 1993-1996 (Box 5:104)
    - Production schedules, undated, 1995 (Box 5:105)
    - Status of articles, undated, 1992-1995 (Box 6:106)
    - Editors' comments, revisions, undated, 1993-1996 (Box 6:107)
    - Headword and blind entries lists, undated, 1992-1995 (Box 6:108)
  - Jackdaw publication (abortive), undated 1976-1980 (Box 6:109)
- Series II: Articles and Book chapters, undated, 1962-1997
  - Why the Cold War Ended: The Latin American Dimension, undated (Box 6:110)
  - Book chapter for Merli/Wilson, eds. Makers of American Diplomacy on Kennan, 1973 (Box 6:111)
  - "Kennan, George F.", article for International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 1978 (Box 6:112)
  - Guide to the Foreign Relations of the United States, Chapter 28, undated, 1978-1982 (Box 6:113)
  - "Pow Ade Mersfelder: Artist in Stalag III-B": article in American History Illustrated, undated, 1982-1983 (Box 6:114)
    - Photocopies of maps and of master index files of Provost Marshal General's office, 1945 (Box 30:781)
  - Remembering Armin Rappaport, 1983 (Box 6:115)
  - Review of Barton Gellman's book Contending With Kennan: Toward a Philosophy of Power, undated, 1984 July - December (Box 6:116)
  - A Research Note: The Historian as Detective: Senator Kenneth Keating, the Missiles in Cuba, and his Mysterious Sources for Diplomatic History, undated, 1985-1986 (Box 6:117)
  - "John F. Kennedy and the World," delivered 18 October 1986; also in J. Richard Snyder's book John F. Kennedy, undated1987 June 10 (Box 6:118)
  - Rethinking a Nuclear Crisis: The Defense of Cuba Theme, undated (Box 6:119)
  - "Explaining the History of American Foreign Relations": a Roundtable for the Journal of American History, 1990 (Box 6:120)
  - "What is Diplomatic History? Defining and Doing American Diplomatic History: A Primer" for Diplomatic History Symposium, 1990 Fall (Box 6:121)
  - "The End of the Cold War and the Illusive Quest for the New World Order", article for the New England Journal of History, New England History Teachers Association Luncheon, 24th Northeast Regional Conference on the Social Studies, Boston, MA, 4 March 1993, undated, 1993 March - September (Box 6:122)
  - "Bowles, Chester", article for the Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations, undated, 1995 (Box 6:123)
  - "When Fear Ruled: Rethinking the Cuban Missile Crisis", for New England Journal of History, 1995 (Box 6:124)
  - "The Limits of Hegemony: The United States and the Cuban Revolution", for Yang Shengmao book Limits of Hegemony, undated, 1994-1996 (Box 6:125)
  - World Health Organization, undated, 1996 (Box 6:126)
  - "U.S. Intervention in Cuba, 1898: Interpretations of the Spanish-American-Cuban- Filipino War"; "U.S. Intervention in Cuba, 1898: the Spanish-American-Cuban-Filipino War Reinterpreted", articles for The History Teacher and OAH Magazine, undated, 1996 February - September (Box 6:127)
  - "In Marshall's Time: Nation-Building in a Transforming World," for Marshall Foundation Symposium (17 October 1996), undated (Box 6:128)
  - Palestine article for the Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations, undated, 1996 (Box 6:129)
  - "Samoa, American", article for the Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations, undated (Box 6:130)
  - "Self-Determination," article for the Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations, undated (Box 6:131)
  - "Kennedy, John F.", (June 1997),for Oxford Companion to American Military History, undated, 1994-1997 (Box 6:132)
  - "We Can Leave it to the Historians": A Question About the Cuban Missile Crisis for Researchers in the Russian Archives," article for SHAFR newsletter on Cuban Missile Crisis, undated 1962 December 29 (Box 6:133)
- Series III: Lectures and Panels, undated, 1964-2002
  - "The New World Order", Campbell University, undated (Box 7:134)
  - "Thinking About the Cold War", Campbell University, undated (Box 7:135)
  - "The Roots of Vietnam", University of Connecticut Teach-in (13 November 1969), undated (Box 7:136)
  - "The Origins of the Cold War: A Suggested Interpretation", Conference on the Cold War, Santa Clara University (10 May 1971), undated (Box 7:137)
  - "Truman Doctrine and Marshall Plan", American Historical Association annual meeting (28 December 1972, New Orleans, Louisiana, undated, 1971-1972 (Box 7:138)
  - "Power and the Origins of the Cold War",, Kansas State University (7 March 1973), undated (Box 7:139)
  - "The Early Cold War", Missouri Valley History Conference, (8-10 March 1973, Omaha, Nebraska)-- T. Paterson, moderator, undated, 1972-1973 (Box 7:140)
  - "The Origins of the Cold War", University of Wisconsin, River Falls (25 January 1974), undated (Box 7:141)
  - "Origins of the Cold War", History 299 (October 1974-1975); "The Legacy and Lessons of World War II: What was the World Like in 1945?", University of Connecticut paper, undated, 1974 (Box 7:142)
  - "The European Defense Community", American Historical Association panel (27 December 1974), undated (Box 7:143)
  - "The Economic Causes of the Cold War", University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill (24 February 1976), 1976 February (Box 7:144)
  - "The Collapse of Appeasement and Isolationism", Organization of American Historians panel (9 April 1976, St. Louis session), undated, 1975-1976 (Box 7:145)
  - "Foreign Policy in a Free Society: Role of Public Opinion", Sparkman Symposium (21 May 1976, Huntsville, Alabama), 1976 April - May (Box 7:146)
  - "The Origins of the Cold War", U.S. Military Academy, West Point (30 November 1976), undated, 1976 August - October (Box 7:147)
  - "The United States and Emerging Nationalism in the 1950's and 1960's", Hotchkiss School (23 May 23 1977), undated (Box 7:148)
  - "Kissinger and Détente", Taft School (24 May 24 1977), undated (Box 7:149)
  - "Cuba and the United States, 1930's-1960's", Sparkman Symposium (27-28 April 1978), University of Alabama, Huntsville, undated, 1977-1978 (Box 7:150)
  - Sino-American Relations Conference (9-11 June 1978, Mt. Kisco, New York, undated, 1978 April - June (Box 7:151)
  - "John F. Kennedy and the Cuban Missile Crisis", U.S. Military Academy, West Point (30 November 1978), undated, 1978 June - November (Box 7:152)
  - "Comments on Papers by Sbrega, White, and Sellen: Comparative Perspectives on Indochina During World War II",, T. Paterson as American Historical Association commentator for panel "Comparative Perspectives on Indochina During World War II" (December 1978, San Francisco, California, 1977-1978 (Box 7:153)
  - "Truman, Public Opinion, and Congress",, Rutgers University (7 December 1978, Newark, New Jersey), undated (Box 7:154)
  - "If Europe, Why Not China? Applying the Containment Doctrine, 1947-1949", University of Connecticut Colloquium (21 February 1979), undated (Box 7:155)
  - "Why the Cold War Came: The International System as One Explanation", University of Winnipeg (March 1979), undated (Box 7:156)
  - "The United States and East Asia in the Early Cold War", New England Conference of the Association for Asian Studies (20-21 October 1979), 1979 January - October (Box 7:157)
  - "United States Senate and Vietnam", Organization of American Historians conference (April 1981, Detroit, Michigan, undated, 1980 February 25 (Box 7:158)
  - SHAFR conference (1982, Boston, Massachusetts), undated, 1982 June - July (Box 7:159)
  - U.S. Air Force Academy lecture (1984), undated, 1984 August - December (Box 7:160)
  - "John F. Kennedy and the Cuban Missile Crisis", Brown University (15 March 1984); Shippensburg University of Pennsylvania (22 March 1984); University of Oregon (12 November 1984); U.S. Air Force Academy(20 November 1984); Colgate University (23 April 1986); University of Auckland, Australia-New Zealand American Studies Association(14 May 1986, New Jersey); Rutgers University (9 March 1987), undated (Box 7:161)
  - "Truman's Foreign Policy: Europe", University of Missouri, Kansas City (April 1984); Rivier College (April 1984); U.S. Air Force Academy (November 1984), undated (Box 7:162)
  - "Rethinking American Foreign Policy: The Origins of the Cold War and the Vietnam War", CAIS History conference, Pomfret School (22 April 1986), undated, 1985-1986 (Box 7:163)
  - Twelfth Australian and New Zealand American Studies Association conference, Auckland University (12-15 May 1986), 1985-1986 (Box 7:164)
  - Kennedy Symposium, University of Wisconsin, LaCrosse (17-18 October 1986), undated, 1985-1986 (Box 7:165)
  - "The Truman Doctrine and its Origins", Fifth Annual Fulbright Institute Symposium: "Europe and The United States: Forty Years After the Truman Doctrine and Marshall Plan", University of Arkansas (5-6 April 1987), undated, 1987 January - March (Box 7:166)
  - "Toward Spheres of Influence: United States Postwar Planning and Soviet-American Relations", conference in the Soviet Union (June 1987), undated (Box 7:167)
  - "John F. Kennedy and the Cuban Missile Crisis", Auburn University (9 November 1987), undated (Box 7:168)
  - "The Kennedys' Fixation: The War Against Cuba" (long version, containing more examples), University of Connecticut Foreign Policy Seminar (February 1988); Sayre School (February 1989, Kentucky); University of Puerto Rico (November 1989), undated (Box 7:169)
  - "Leadership Through Authorship: George F. Kennan's Quest for Foreign Policy Influence", University of Toledo (3 May 1988), undated (Box 7:170)
  - Lecture on George Kennan's The American Diplomacy and Memoirs for program "Public Leadership and Western Literature", University of Toledo (5 May 1988), undated, 1986-1988 (Box 7:171)
  - "John F. Kennedy and the Cuban Missile Crisis", University of North Carolina (February 1989), undated (Box 7:172)
  - "John F. Kennedy and the Cuban Missile Crisis", 1989 David A. Sayre History Symposium: "Crisis and the American Presidency" (25 February 1989), 1988-1989 (Box 7:173)
  - "Why the Cold War Ended: The Latin American Dimension", Yale University (29 March 1991), undated, 1990-1993 (Box 7:174)
  - "Comments on Kunz and Little Papers",, Organization of American Historians panel, 1991 April (Box 7:175)
  - "The End of the Cold War and the New World Order", Phi Alpha Theta, University of Connecticut (April 1991), undated (Box 7:176)